<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?notoc?>
<!DOCTYPE wga-document
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD WGA Study DTD v2.0n 20070315//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/gap/2.0/wga-study2.dtd">
<wga-document wga-document-id="phd008760" wga-document-type="protocol" wga-document-version="1" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
          <front>
                    <study id="phs002453">
                              <study-institution>NHLBI</study-institution>
                              <study-name>Million Veteran Program (MVP) Summary Results from Non-Sensitive Omics Studies</study-name>
                    </study>
                    <source-document-meta>
                              <title-group>
                                        <title>README_MVP_gwPheWAS_vJuly2024.docx</title>
                              </title-group>
                    </source-document-meta>
                    <document-meta>
                              <title-group>
                                        <title>README MVP gwPheWAS</title>
                              </title-group>
                    </document-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
                    <sec id="sec1">
                              <title>MVP gwPheWAS Basic Information</title>
                              <p>These summary statistics are the result of the VA Million Veteran Program (MVP) gwPheWAS effort (collaboration between the US Departments of Veterans Affairs and Energy).
                                        For full details, please see our publication in Science and our methods preprint on BioRxiv. For additional questions please contact the corresponding authors of
                                        these publications or email <email>MVP_gwPheWAS@va.gov</email>. </p>
                              <p>This analysis was run twice in order to respond to evolving recommendations and guidelines around determination of genetic ancestry, race, and ethnicity. We used our
                                        previous “harmonized ancestry and race/ethnicity” (HARE) definition initially then followed with genetically inferred ancestry (GIA). Both sets of results are
                                        available for download via the dbGaP ftp site, however, the GIA results are the focus of the main manuscript and only these results have been processed into dbGaP’s
                                        browsable website and viewer. We refined our analysis plan based on lessons learned from the HARE analysis therefore there are slight differences between the
                                        analyses, which are listed below. Detailed methods for the HARE analysis are attached as an appendix as they are not included in the Science publication. </p>
                              <table-wrap id="t1">
                                        <table frame="border" rules="all" border="1">
                                                  <thead>
                                                            <tr>
                                                                      <th/>
                                                                      <th align="center"><bold>HARE</bold></th>
                                                                      <th align="center"><bold>GIA</bold></th>
                                                            </tr>
                                                  </thead>
                                                  <tbody>
                                                            <tr>
                                                                      <td>Quantitative Traits</td>
                                                                      <td>Raw and inverse-normalized trait values analyzed</td>
                                                                      <td>Only Inverse-normalized trait values analyzed</td>
                                                            </tr>
                                                            <tr>
                                                                      <td>Sex-specific Traits</td>
                                                                      <td>Not analyzed</td>
                                                                      <td>Analyzed and restricted to only the specific biological sex affected</td>
                                                            </tr>
                                                  </tbody>
                                        </table>
                              </table-wrap>
                              <p>The VA considers several conditions to be stigmatizing or sensitive therefore have not been included. These include HIV status, sickle cell disease status, and some
                                        outcomes relating to substance use/abuse. As the latter fell within the phecode category of “Mental Disorders”, none of the phecodes in this category have been
                                        deposited into dbGaP. A future release is anticipated to include phecodes from this category which have been approved for distribution. Additionally, in order to
                                        reduce privacy and reidentification concerns, only population-specific analyses with at least 500 cases were uploaded to dbGaP despite a cutoff of 200 cases for
                                        inclusion in the meta-analysis. </p>
                              <p>Please see Data Dictionary for additional information on phecode definitions and case/control/total counts. If there are any discrepancies between files with regards to
                                        these counts, the summary statistics results file is correct. This is also helpful for determining which tar file(s) contain your phenotype(s) of interest. </p>
                              <p>Please see our GitHuB repository for detailed methods information and code (<ext-link xlink:href="https://github.com/exascale-genomics/SAIGE-GPU/">https://github.com/exascale-genomics/SAIGE-GPU/</ext-link>). </p>
                              <p><bold><underline>Key References</underline></bold></p>
                              <ref-list>
                                        <ref>
                                                  <citation>Verma A, Huffman JE, Rodriguez A, Conery M, Lui M, et al. Diversity and Scale: Genetic Architecture of 2,068 Traits in the VA Million Veteran
                                                            Program. Science. 2024 July 19 doi: 10.1126/science.adj1182</citation>
                                        </ref>
                                        <ref>
                                                  <citation>Rodriguez A, Kim Y, et al. Accelerating Genome- and Phenome-Wide Association Studies using GPUs - A case study using data from the Million
                                                            Veteran Program. bioRxiv [Preprint]. 2024 May 22 doi: 10.1101/2024.05.17.594583. PMID: 38826407 </citation>
                                        </ref>
                                        <ref>
                                                  <citation>Fang H, et al. Harmonizing Genetic Ancestry and Self-identified Race/Ethnicity in Genome-wide Association Studies. Am J Hum Genet. 2019 Oct
                                                            3;105(4):763-772. doi: 10.1016/j.ajhg.2019.08.012. PMID: 31564439 </citation>
                                        </ref>
                              </ref-list>
                    </sec>
                    <sec id="sec2">
                              <title>Methods gwPheWAS [HARE]</title>
                              <sec id="sec2.1">
                                        <title>Million Veteran Program (MVP)</title>
                                        <p>The VA Million Veteran Program (MVP) is a national cohort launched in 2011 designed to study the contributions of genetics, lifestyle, and military exposures to
                                                  health and disease among US Veterans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1">1</xref></sup>. Blood biospecimens were collected for DNA isolation and genotyping, and the biorepository
                                                  was linked with the VA EHR, which includes diagnosis codes (International Classification of Diseases ninth revision [ICD-9] and tenth revision [ICD-10]),
                                                  laboratory measures, and detailed survey questionnaires collected at the time of enrollment for all Veterans followed in the healthcare system up to
                                                  September 2019. </p>
                              </sec>
                              <sec id="sec2.2">
                                        <title>Genotyping, Quality Control, and Imputation</title>
                                        <p>Specimen collection and genotype quality control have been described in detail before<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2">2,3</xref></sup>. In brief, blood specimens were collected at
                                                  recruitment sites across the country then shipped within 24 hours to the VA Central Biorepository in Boston, MA for processing and storage. Study
                                                  participants were genotyped using a customized Affymetrix Axiom biobank array (the MVP 1.0 Genotyping Array), containing over 730,000 variants. Duplicate
                                                  samples were excluded as well as samples with observed heterozygosity greater than the expected heterozygosity, missing genotype call rate greater than
                                                  2.5%, or incongruence between sex inferred from genetic information and gender extracted from phenotype data. Probes with high missingness (>20%), those
                                                  that were monomorphic, or those with a Hardy Weinberg Equilibrium p&lt;1E-06 in both the overall cohort and within one of the 3 major HARE groups
                                                  (non-Hispanic White, non-Hispanic Black, or Hispanic/Latino). See below for HARE methods. </p>
                                        <p>Population-specific principal components (PCs) were computed using EIGENSOFT v.6<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4">4</xref></sup>. </p>
                                        <p>Genetic imputation was performed to a hybrid imputation panel comprised of the African Genome Resources panel (<ext-link
                                                  xlink:href="https://imputation.sanger.ac.uk/?about=1#referencepanels">https://imputation.sanger.ac.uk/?about=1#referencepanels</ext-link>) and
                                                  1000G p3v5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5">5</xref></sup> using SHAPEIT4 (v 4.1.3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6">6</xref></sup>, and Minimac4<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7">7</xref></sup>. </p>
                              </sec>
                              <sec id="sec2.3">
                                        <title>Ancestry assignment</title>
                                        <p>The harmonized race/ethnicity and genetic ancestry (HARE) approach, developed by MVP, was used to assign individuals to ancestral groups<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8">8</xref></sup>. This machine learning
                                                  algorithm leverages information from both the self-reported race/ethnicity data from the MVP Baseline survey and genotype data to categorized Veterans into
                                                  four mutually exclusive groups: (1) non-Hispanic White (EUR), (2) non-Hispanic Black (AFR), (3) Hispanic or Latino (HIS), or (4) Asian (ASN). </p>
                              </sec>
                              <sec id="sec2.4">
                                        <title>Phenotype Data </title>
                                        <sec id="sec2.4.1">
                                                  <title>EHR-derived clinical outcomes (PheCodes)</title>
                                                  <p>The clinical outcome from EHR was defined by phecodes curated by the MCP Data Core<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9">9</xref></sup>. Each phecode represents ICD codes grouped into clinically relevant
                                                            phenotypes for clinical studies. Using this approach, all ICD codes for all Veterans in MVP were extracted and each assigned a phenotype defined
                                                            by a phecode. ICD-9 and ICD-10 codes were mapped to 1,876 phecodes, as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10">10</xref></sup>. For each phecode, participants with ≥2
                                                            phecode-mapped ICD-9 or ICD-10 codes were defined as cases, whereas those with no instance of a phecode-mapped ICD-9 or ICD-10 code were defined
                                                            as controls. Based on our previous simulation studies of ICD EHR data, populations where the phecode comprises &lt; 200 cases or controls were
                                                            more likely to result in spurious results, and we thus applied this threshold in each of the four HARE-defined ancestry groups. </p>
                                        </sec>
                                        <sec id="sec2.4.2">
                                                  <title>Laboratory measurements</title>
                                                  <p>For quantitative traits, we calculated the minimum, maximum, and mean value across all visits for each participant and analyzed each resulting
                                                            phenotype. Only quantitative traits with data for more than 1000 individuals within each HARE-defined ancestry group were included in the
                                                            analyses. The remaining 69 laboratory measurements that passed quality control were normalized using a rank-based inverse-normal transformation.
                                                            We additionally filtered values are greater than six standard deviations from the mean in order to remove extreme outliers. </p>
                                        </sec>
                                        <sec id="sec2.4.3">
                                                  <title>Survey Questions</title>
                                                  <p>The two surveys (questionnaires) for MVP, as noted previously, were designed to augment data that are contained in the electronic health record of each
                                                            participant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1">1</xref></sup>. As with other study activities and all study materials sent to participants, these documents were approved by the VA Central IRB.
                                                            As participants are enrolled, informed consent and HIPAA authorization forms are scanned by field site staff and sent to the CERC, to be checked
                                                            for accuracy and completeness, and the data are entered in GenISIS. Conceptually, the MVP Baseline Survey was designed to collect information
                                                            regarding demographics, family pedigree, health status, lifestyle habits, military experience, medical history, family history of specific
                                                            illnesses, and physical features. The MVP Lifestyle Survey contains questions from validated instruments in domains selected to provide
                                                            information on sleep and exercise habits, environmental exposures, dietary habits, and sense of well-being. </p>
                                        </sec>
                              </sec>
                              <sec id="sec2.5">
                                        <title>Genetic association analyses</title>
                                        <p>Within each HARE-defined ancestry group (AFR, ASN, EUR, HIS), genetic variants were tested for their association with the trait of interest using generalized
                                                  linear mixed models to account for participant relatedness using a GPU-optimized version of the SAIGE package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11">11</xref></sup> implemented on the U.S. Department of
                                                  Energy Summit supercomputer. Directly genotyped variants were used for step 1 of SAIGE. Imputed genetic dosages were used for step 2 of SAIGE. Variants
                                                  were only included in the GWAS if they had an imputation quality > 0.3 and a minor allele count (MAC) > 20 within the relevant HARE-defined ancestry group.
                                                  Analyses were adjusted for age, sex, and 10 ancestry-specific genetic principal components. </p>
                              </sec>
                              <sec id="sec2.6">
                                        <title>Post-GWAS quality control</title>
                                        <p>GWAS results were filtered using a custom R script loosely based on EasyQC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12">12</xref></sup>. Sanity checks were implemented to remove variants with missing values for major
                                                  summary statistics (effect size, standard error, etc) or with unreasonable values (p-values or allele frequencies with values >1 or &lt;0). Additionally,
                                                  variants were removed that were monomorphic, poorly imputed (r2&lt;0.3) or very rare (minor allele frequency &lt; 0.0001) in just the subset of individuals
                                                  included in the GWAS. </p>
                              </sec>
                              <sec id="sec2.7">
                                        <title>Meta-Analysis</title>
                                        <p>Multi-ancestry meta-analysis was performed using the inverse-variance weighted method as implemented in GWAMA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13">13</xref></sup>. Meta-analysis results then underwent the same
                                                  quality control procedures as the GWAS results. Imputation quality filters were not implemented however an additional filter was added to exclude variants
                                                  that were specific to only one HARE-defined ancestry group. </p>
                              </sec> 
                    </sec> 
                    
          </body>
          <back>
                   <app-group>
                             <app id="refs"><sec>
                                       <title>References</title>
                                       <ref-list>
                                                 <ref id="bibr1">
                                                           <label>1</label>
                                                           <citation>Gaziano JM, Concato J, Brophy M, et al. Million Veteran Program: A mega-biobank to study genetic influences on health and disease. J Clin
                                                                     Epidemiol 2016;70:214–23. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr2">
                                                           <label>2</label>
                                                           <citation>Klarin D, Damrauer SM, Cho K, et al. Genetics of blood lipids among ~300,000 multi-ethnic participants of the Million Veteran Program. Nat Genet
                                                                     2018;50(11):1514–23. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr3">
                                                           <label>3</label>
                                                           <citation>Hunter-Zinck H, Shi Y, Li M, et al. Genotyping Array Design and Data Quality Control in the Million Veteran Program. Am J Hum Genet
                                                                     2020;106(4):535–48. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr4">
                                                           <label>4</label>
                                                           <citation>Price AL, Patterson NJ, Plenge RM, Weinblatt ME, Shadick NA, Reich D. Principal components analysis corrects for stratification in genome-wide
                                                                     association studies. Nat Genet 2006;38(8):904–9. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr5">
                                                           <label>5</label>
                                                           <citation>1000 Genomes Project Consortium, Auton A, Brooks LD, et al. A global reference for human genetic variation. Nature 2015;526(7571):68–74.
                                                           </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr6">
                                                           <label>6</label>
                                                           <citation>Delaneau O, Zagury J-F, Robinson MR, Marchini JL, Dermitzakis ET. Accurate, scalable and integrative haplotype estimation. Nat Commun
                                                                     2019;10(1):5436. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr7">
                                                           <label>7</label>
                                                           <citation>Howie B, Fuchsberger C, Stephens M, Marchini J, Abecasis GR. Fast and accurate genotype imputation in genome-wide association studies through
                                                                     pre-phasing. Nat Genet 2012;44(8):955–9. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr8">
                                                           <label>8</label>
                                                           <citation>Fang H, Hui Q, Lynch J, et al. Harmonizing Genetic Ancestry and Self-identified Race/Ethnicity in Genome-wide Association Studies. Am J Hum Genet
                                                                     2019;105(4):763–72. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr9">
                                                           <label>9</label>
                                                           <citation>Song RJ, Ho YL, Schubert P, et al. Phenome-wide association of 1809 phenotypes and COVID-19 disease progression in the Veterans Health
                                                                     Administration Million Veteran Program. PLoS One 2021;16(5):e0251651. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr10">
                                                           <label>10</label>
                                                           <citation>Denny JC, Ritchie MD, Basford MA, et al. PheWAS: demonstrating the feasibility of a phenome-wide scan to discover gene-disease associations.
                                                                     Bioinformatics 2010;26(9):1205–10. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr11">
                                                           <label>11</label>
                                                           <citation>Zhou W, Nielsen JB, Fritsche LG, et al. Efficiently controlling for case-control imbalance and sample relatedness in large-scale genetic
                                                                     association studies. Nat Genet 2018;50(9):1335–41. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr12">
                                                           <label>12</label>
                                                           <citation>Winkler TW, Day FR, Croteau-Chonka DC, et al. Quality control and conduct of genome-wide association meta-analyses. Nat Protoc
                                                                     2014;9(5):1192–212. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                                 <ref id="bibr13">
                                                           <label>13</label>
                                                           <citation>Mägi R, Morris AP. GWAMA: software for genome-wide association meta-analysis. BMC Bioinformatics 2010;11:288. </citation>
                                                 </ref>
                                       </ref-list> 
                             </sec>
                             </app>
                   </app-group>
          
          </back>
</wga-document>
